Hello and welcome back to another video
with ItsDrDan and today we are going to be
learning about the conservation of mass.
So what is it all about?
Well, the conservation of mass is
a law, so let's quickly refer to
what is a theory versus law, just so
we're familiar with those concepts.
So a theory is a proposed explanation
that is based on the examination of fact.
So if you see a bunch of observations,
you're measuring a bunch of things.
And then you want to theorize exactly
what it is that you're seeing.
So this is something about like
how maybe new medicines or new
vaccines or how maybe we can make
rockets that can go to the moon.
It's all trying to answer
those why type of questions.
Now, a law is something that's based on
a natural process, meaning that it's, it
behaves exact same way, no matter what.
Because that is how our world works.
So, for example, the law of gravity.
No matter what, if I take a, an
object and I were to drop it,
it's going to fall no matter what.
Um, so for this one, the law of
conservation of mass is one of those.
Now what is this all about?
Well, it's about that mass
cannot be created nor destroyed
via chemical reactions.
So however much reactant you have going
in or how much mass, you should get
it out as a different type of product.
So if you measure a certain mass at
the very beginning and it combined with
another ingredient that you measured to,
you should get the same amount afterwards.
Now, bear in mind, there could be all
kinds of things that could go wrong,
maybe the reaction is not perfectly
complete, but it is something that's
been observed time and time again
for as long as humanity has existed,
it is a constant law that exists.
Let's take a look at
what this is all about.
As I said before, this is all
about how we can conserve mass.
Meaning that let's say if I have
a reaction and I have a bunch of
little atoms trying to go in to
this chemical reaction and I want
to ask what exactly will happen?
What should I get out afterwards?
So if I have three yellow atoms and two
red ones and they were to go through
the chemical reaction as reactants,
according to the law of conservation
of mass, All of them should come out.
Now, if it's a chemical change or
a chemical reaction, so where we
have change occurring and we can
see that change, where everything
makes a brand new product.
Notice how I still have
three yellow atoms.
Two red ones, but they look completely
different because a reaction took place.
However, I still have the same mass
because if I add up all those individual
atoms, I will still get the same number.
So atoms are rearranged
during a chemical reaction.
They are never lost.
So they always exist as something
whether it's a product or a reactant,
meaning that the mass of any element
at the beginning of a reaction is will
always be equal to the mass of the
elements at the end of the reaction.
So if I have all these little
pieces, you should be able to add
them up, and you should have the
same amount of mass on both sides.
So the mass of the reactants always
equals the mass of the products.
And so let's take a look at how
we can use this in some examples.
Let's say I have a combustion
reaction, meaning that we're
going to burn something.
So similar to, let's say if you have a gas
stove or a propane grill at home, you burn
the gas with, and it needs oxygen for it
to breathe in order for that to happen.
Well, what does it make afterwards
if you were to burn something?
Well, one of the things that you
might see or notice is smoke, right?
So CO2.
One of the other ingredients that
can occur as well will be made as
well as water, which you can see is
water vapor, um, as well, it's one of
the other things that gets created.
So if I have a combustion reaction here, I
have methane gas and I have oxygen atoms.
Notice how they're all together.
And it's going to combust, and we're
going to be making CO2 and water.
Now, let's say we were
to measure this reaction.
Meaning we're going to measure the mass of
each of the different ingredients in it.
So, I measured it, and I found that
there were 16 grams of methane in
the reaction, and I notice that
there's also 64 grams of oxygen, and
it combusts to make CO2 and water.
Okay?
Great.
So we want to highlight all those
important pieces of information
as we go through these, right?
It's something I've talked about in
many of my videos as we go through them.
Put the information together,
figure out what you're given.
Now it says we also measure 44
grams of CO2, which is created.
Now I'm asking, or I desire,
is how much water should we
make after a complete reaction.
So how much water should there be?
Now what are we going to do?
I already have a balanced chemical
reaction, which for many students
at this point is something you
will learn later in the semester.
So we're going to write down all the
pieces of information that we were given.
So we have 16 grams of methane,
we have 64 grams of oxygen,
and we have 44 grams of CO2.
And we want to know how many grams
of H2O do I have in this problem.
Now, from this, if you remember from what
I said before, the mass of the reactants
is equal to the mass of the products.
So what exactly should I do?
So this is just simply
just a algebra problem.
We'll add up both sides and solve
for x essentially, which is water.
So if I take this and re and kind of
rewrite it for ourselves, let's do that.
So we have 16 grams of CO2.
We have 64 grams of O2 as reactants.
And that's equal to 44
grams of CO2 plus X.
So let's solve for X.
So on the left hand side we'll
have a total of 80 grams.
We will move over the 44
grams from both sides.
And what we will see as a result is
that x is going to be equal to 36 grams.
So 80 minus 44 is 36.
Now, does that make sense?
Well, let's take a look at it.
So if we know that water
was 36 grams, which is H2O.
And we know that CO2 is 44 grams.
What is the total?
80 grams.
And what was the thing that we
had on the left side earlier?
Well if you notice, earlier
we had 80 grams as reactants.
So notice that the law of conservation
of mass exists and we have the
same amount of mass on each sides.
So if you have a complete reaction,
Or even something that maybe it
doesn't completely go, go through,
if you measure everything, you
should still have the same amount.
Okay.
So this has been the conservation of mass.
I hope that this video helped you.
Thank you so much for listening
and please hit that like and
subscribe button if you haven't.
Uh, there'll be more chemistry content
to come and thank you all so much.
Bye now.